Okay בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*, today is thirty-sixth day of the עומר
*Omer*, third פרק perek, *Perek* of קינים *Kinnim*. Thirty-sixth? That's right. Okay.
We start at the bottom of כג עמוד ב base. *Chaf Gimmel
Amud Bais* here, continuing the pagination from מעילה *Me'ila*. Beginning of the
third פרק perek. *Perek* of קינים *Kinnim*. Now, this third פרק perek,
*Perek* really is pretty much a parallel or links to the first
פרק perek. *Perek*. The language is the same and in a way
it's really commenting on the first פרק perek. *Perek*. So let's take
a look. במה דברים אמורים *Bameh Devarim Amurim*. When is all of
this said? Meaning everything we said about the first פרק parak. *Perek*
about, you know, an עולה olah *Olah* gets mixed up and or
two חובות *Chovos* get mixed up, two groups get mixed up, how
many you can bring. When is all that said? בכהן הנמלך *B'chohen
Hanimlach*. If the כהן kohen *Kohen* comes and asks us advice, what
should I do? So of course we advise the כהן kohen *Kohen*
to say to say, bring only the number of birds that you'll
make sure won't get you into a problem, right? Now, of course
I have a friend who likes saying, it's a lot easier to
ask for forgiveness than for permission.
And that seems to be, what do you think about that?
Yeah, that seems to be the point of this פרק parak. *Perek*
because the first פרק perek *Perek* is all about asking permission. Yes,
permission, you have to do it exactly right and don't bring even
one bird that might be the wrong bird and therefore it very
much limits what you can bring because you don't want to bring
even one thing possibly wrong. But if you didn't ask permission and
you went ahead and did it, then you might have actually succeeded
in making more of them כשר kasher? *kosher* because in the process
you did some things wrong but you'll also would have done some
things right, you know, if you go ahead and do everything. And
that's what this פרק perek, *Perek* talks about, somebody who didn't ask
permission, went ahead and did everything and as a result more things
are כשר kasher? *kosher* because some things are also going to be
פסול posul *pasul*. So let's take a look. במה דברים אמורים *Bameh
Devarim Amurim*. That's what this פרק perek, *Perek* is really devoted to.
What is this about? בכהן הנמלך *B'chohen Hanimlach*. A כהן kohen *Kohen*
who asks permission. אבל בכהן שאינו נמלך *Aval b'chohen she'eino nimlach*. If
you didn't ask permission and went ahead and just did it. So
אחת לזו ואחת לזו *Achas l'zu v'achas l'zu*, you'll see the language
here is directly parallels the first פרק *Perek*. שתים לזו ושתים לזו
*Shtayim l'zu v'shtayim l'zu*, שלש לזו ושלש לזו *Shalosh l'zu v'shalosh l'zu*.
You have one in one woman or group that has one pair
and another one pair or two pairs and two pairs or three
pairs and three pairs. Equal sized groups, non-differentiated.
And who remembers the rule when you have two equal sized non-differentiated
groups that mix up, how many can you bring?
The smallest one.
The smallest one which is the special case of equal size, that's
true, and in the special case of equal size is half because
they're equal sized. That's correct. So you can bring half because as
long as you're bringing half and doing half as עולות olahs *Olos*,
half as חטאות chatases *Chataos*, you're definitely safe. This guy went ahead,
didn't ask any permission. What did he do? עשה כולם למעלה asah
kulam l'malah, *Asa kulam lemala*. Now if you put all of them
on the top half. So if they're all on the top half,
he treated all of them as an עולה olah, *Olah* then and
only half of them are עולות olahs *Olos*, so half will be
כשר kasher? *kosher*. מחצה כשר מחצה פסול Mechtza kasher mechtza posul. *Mechtza
kasher mechtza pasul*. Half a כשר kosher. *kosher* half a פסול pasul.
*pasul*. He did everything on the top, so we know half were
עולות olahs *Olos*, half were חטאות chatases *Chataos* but he made them
all עולות olahs *Olos* so half are going to be good. כולם
למטה *Kulam lemata*. Everything below like a חטאת chatas *Chatas*. מחצה כשר
מחצה פסול mechtza kasher mechtza posul. *Mechtza kasher mechtza pasul*. Same story.
He made everything a חטאת chatas, *Chatas* but only half of them
are חטאות chattasos, *Chataos* so half is good. מחצה למעלה l'maala, ומחצה
למטה *Mechtza lemala u'mechtza lemata*. So he did half above and half
below. Of course it would be nice if he got the halves
right, but who's to say? Okay. את שלמעלה מחצה כשר מחצה פסול
mechtza kasher mechtza posul, ואת שלמטה מחצה כשר מחצה פסול mechetza kasher
mechetza pasul, *Es shelemala mechtza kasher mechtza pasul v'es shelemata mechtza kasher
mechtza pasul*. Each the part on the half top half is half
good and the top on the bottom half is half good. Why
is that? Because let's imagine, right, worst just the two extremes and
you'll see it. One extreme is that the top half is fifty
percent from group A, fifty percent from group B, right? And the
bottom half the same. If that's true, they're all good, right? Because
you have half of A and half of B, half of A
on top half of A on bottom, half of B on top
half of B on bottom. In that case it's one hundred percent
good. You with me? Yes. Let's go to the other extreme. The
top half is one hundred percent A, the bottom half is one
hundred percent B. So the top half how much is okay? Half.
And the bottom half how much is okay? Half. So you can
only assume the worst case scenario so you can only assume half
good, half not good. So actually
here, could he have gotten everything wrong? No, how could you? They're
undifferentiated. You either have one hundred percent A, one hundred percent B
or fifty percent A, fifty percent B or something in between. So
in the worst case scenario one hundred percent A, one hundred percent
B, it's half good, half bad. So in this
case the post-facto, the after-the-fact is no different than the before-the-fact. The
before-the-fact you ask permission, you're told bring half. Here you didn't ask
permission, you did everything, how much is good? Half. Okay. So in
this case it's the same whether you ask permission or didn't once
you did it. It's half good, it's the same as had you
asked permission. Now, but we're going to do other cases where it
matters the next משניות *Mishnayos*. Yes?
So is there no consideration about is there any any negative effect
of intentionally doing something that you know is going to be פסול
pasul *pasul*?
Well you don't want to consciously be מקריב makriv *makriv* a פסול
Pasul. *pasul* קרבן korban. *korban*. Is there like, are you
saying like like is there some punishment? Now is there a prohibition?
You know that's a good point. We're always assuming that it's אסור
to be מקריב makriv, a פסול Pasul קרבן. korban
What exactly is it technically a negative prohibition or not? This is,
yeah.
You find those helpful?
I don't know.
Okay. Anyway, you know I don't know that's a good question. We
certainly assume that you're not allowed to, whether we actually say that
technically it's like a biblical prohibition to do so, or somehow it's
like implicit in the sanctity that you're not supposed to violate the
sanctity of it?
Yeah, wouldn't there be some inhibition on his part?
Yeah, but like maybe he
didn't, maybe sometimes we know that כהנים kohanim were you know, I
mean the גמרא Gemara often says that they were like more concerned
about laws of טומאה וטהרה tuma v'tahara than they were about like
other issues. You know sometimes they would do פיגול pigul and they
wouldn't matter, bother with פיגול, pigul, but you know so not everybody
was as scrupulous as we would always want them to be and
maybe he even didn't know, he didn't realize that there was a
problem. He just was under the impression that it was all one
big undifferentiated group and he had the permission to split them in
half, you know what I mean? Maybe he so could also have
been a mistake. But yeah, but you're right. I mean clearly you're
not supposed to, exactly whether you know the nature of the prohibition
I'd have to check. Okay so that's the first case. First case
is two equal-sized groups and whether you ask permission or did it
afterwards, at the end of the day we can only assume half
are good. But now we're going to get the cases where it
is going to make a difference whether you did, whether you asked
permission or did it afterwards. אחת לזו ושתים לזו, Achas l'zu v'shtayim
l'zu, משנה Mishna ב. אחת לזו ושתים לזו ושלש לזו ועשר לזו
ומאה לזו. Achas l'zu v'shtayim l'zu v'shalosh l'zu v'eser l'zu v'mea l'zu.
Different size groups. One, two, three, five, ten, one hundred.
Now here David what's the rule if you ask permission? No you
said it before. Different size groups the rule is, no the smallest.
Right? You could only bring the smallest because as soon as you
bring more than the smallest number, right what's going to happen? Let's
say the smallest group was, was one, right you know, so you
as soon as you would bring three birds what might happen? What
might happen is that you brought the עולה olah of the smallest
group and then you brought a חטאת chatas, from something else and
then you brought another חטאת, chatat excuse me, and then you brought
another עולה, olah. but that other עולה olah you brought was from
the smallest group, so you've now brought two עולות olahs from the
smallest group and the second one has to be a חטאת, chatat
so anything more than the smallest number you might be bringing the
one left from the smallest group in the wrong way. So that's
the rule that if they're different size group and you ask permission
it has to be the smallest number. Now what happens if you
didn't ask permission?
כולן למעלה, Kulan l'maala, you did all of them on the top.
מחצה כשר מחצה פסול. Mechtza Kosher Mechtza Pasul. Right? That's, you know
if you had a group let's just take the extreme, you had
a group of one hundred mixed up with a group of one.
So if you asked permission you can't take any more than you
know than two birds, than one full group, because any more you
might be like I said taking a bird that's already been designated
and taking it the wrong way. But you didn't ask permission, so
you did one hundred and one pairs on top of the מזבח.
mizbeach. So how much is כשר? kasher. Well no, how much after
the fact is כשר? kosher, One hundred and one pairs on the
top of the מזבח, mizbeach, right one hundred and one, how much
is כשר? kosher. Half. Right half, you brought one hundred and one
חטאת עולה chatas-olah pairs, so all of the עולות olos? are כשר.
kosher. Okay half is כשר. kosher. So if you did it למעלה,
מחצה כשר מחצה פסול. Mechtza Kosher Mechtza Pasul, כולן למטה, Kulan l'mata,
you did one hundred and one pairs below. So מחצה כשר kosher?
מחצה פסול, mechetza pasul, same drill. You have one hundred and one
חטאת עולה chatas-olah pairs, you did it below, all of the חטאות
chattasos are כשר, kosher all of the עולות olos? are not כשר.
kosher. So see how much you see what you got out of
not listening. If you asked permission you would have been told one
pair. Now you didn't ask permission, actually you know you've got fifty
and a half pairs that were כשר. kosher. Okay. חציו למעלה וחציו
למטה. Chetyo l'maala v'chetyo l'mata. Now let's say you split them. המרובה
כשר. Hameruba kasher. The maximum one is כשר. kosher How does this
work that the maximum one is כשר? kosher So let me, let
me demonstrate it to you in the following way.
Let's assume that,
let's assume I don't know for argument's sake you have one hundred
and sixteen, you have one group of one hundred and one group
of sixteen. Okay, so on the top you're going to do one
hundred and sixteen birds and on the bottom one hundred and sixteen
birds. Okay, right? This is where the עולות olos? go and this
is where the חטאות chataot go. Now how many definite good עולות
olos. do we know are here? So this is the way you
do it. You assume worst-case scenario is you assume that all of
this is group B, this is group A. Worst-case scenario is you
assume all of group B was this is like pairs,
right? Pairs, which isn't so... all of group, so all of you
assume all of group B is on top, right sixteen pairs. Are
you with me? Thirty-two are on top. Yes, is that clear? Okay,
and then this remaining this is 84, right? From group A. Yes?
Yes? Everybody with me? Okay. So that's why that worst-case scenario because
if I could have everything here by group A, right, then I
would if I had a whole hundred here by group A, then
that whole hundred would be כשר kosher. because a hundred above a
hundred below. Is that clear? The best-case scenario. What's the best-case scenario?
Best-case scenario is you get everything right. 100 of A and 16
of B above, and 100 of A and 16 of B below,
then everything is כשר. kosher That's best-case scenario. Worst-case scenario is you
take the 16 below and you move it above. Yes? That's worst-case
scenario. Then only the 84 of A are כשר. kosher Yes? Now,
of the remaining here, of the remaining 32, how many are going
to be כשר kosher as עולות? olos Well, let's
consider both extremes. In this scenario, how many are כשר kosher. as
עולות? olos 16, right?
You guys right? Because they're all from B and 16 are כשר.
kosher In the opposite extreme, with the best-case scenario where there is
100 from A, how many are כשר kosher, as עולות? olos, Also
the first 16, right? This first 16 are going to be כשר
kosher, as עולות. olos. If they're from B, they're כשר kosher because
it's half of B. If they're from A, they're certainly כשר. kosher
So how many כשר kosher. עולות olot. do we have in the
end? 100. Okay.
You see that? So you've got to basically, if it's the best-case
scenario, 116 are כשר, kosher. right? But if it's the worst-case scenario,
then you've got 84, but you've also got 16 עולות olot כשר,
kosher. and the same is true at the bottom. Just flip it,
and the same is true at the bottom. So even in the
worst-case scenarios, you know you have the 100 כשר kosher, עולות, olot
100 כשר kosher. חטאות, chataot which is המרובה כשר. hamurba kosher. The
size of the biggest group is כשר. kosher? Okay.
Yes? Clear? Okay.
But I'm just trying to...
By the way, if the groups were equal size, right? So what
would... so המרובה כשר hamurba kosher would say half of, you know,
would say half, so the case of equal size and half is
just a special case of the rule that המרובה כשר. hamurba kosher.
Okay, so meaning the רובא's ruba 100 pairs, right? Then you're going
to say 100 pairs are כשר. kosher? 100 חטאות chataot and 100
עולות. olahs, Okay.
What about, you know, I just... I remember a
case that רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar says, oh וזו היא ראש, v'zu
hi rosh, you know, remember? Like that was the one. Like, if
you'd mean what you're providing for, like if you did it we
could have said that those were the ones that belonged there all
the time?
Yeah, in general we don't. I mean, we'll sometimes say that by
certain דרבננ'ס derabbanans or whatever.
Remember the case of רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar with the ראש rosh
and the... you know, ובין הראש ובין הרגל מן הראש ומן הרגל?
v'bein harosh u-vein haregel min harosh u-min haregel?
Yeah, that's a good point. You have a very good memory, Michael.
But that was a difficult position in general and I have to
check that, but that was a special case. Obviously normally you can't
assume things work out the way they... you have to assume worst-case
scenario. Okay. So that's what you did. You had different-sized groups, right?
And you did it... and so then the rule is if you
did it half and half, the size the bigger group is that
number. It's obviously not all necessarily from the bigger group, but if
the bigger group was 100 pairs, then 100 pairs are כשר. kasher?
And as I said, if they're equal sizes, that's just a special
case of the law that the larger size is כשר, kasher, which
means half of them is כשר. kasher, Okay. זה כלל. Zeh klal.
This is the rule. כל מקום שאתה יכול לחלק את הקינין שלא
יהא משל אשה אחת. Kol makom she-ata yachol lechalek et hakinim shelo
yehe mi-shel isha achas.
If you can divide it in a way that would make sure
that it would not be just of a one woman, שלא יהא
משל אשה אחת בין למעלה ובין למטה, shelo yehe mi-shel isha achas
bein lemala u-vein lemata, and you can ensure that one woman's things
are not both above and below. It's a very funny formulation, but
it means if you can do it so that one woman's קרבנות
korbanot are not both above and below. Meaning, meaning, if it's equal
sizes, what happens when it's equal sizes?
When it's equal sizes, right, it's 100 and 100, right?
It's possible that one woman's are all above and one woman's are
all below, theoretically. And if that's true, that one is all above,
then how much... if everything of mine was done above, how many
is going to be כשר? kasher. 50. And if everything of yours
is below, how many are going to be כשר? kasher? 50. So
that's the case where it's possible... possible meaning this is worst-case scenario
is that all are above, all are below. In this case of
116 of pairs, right? It's impossible that one person's would be all
above.
These certainly... these could be all above, but A's could not all
be above. Some has to... right? Because A is a total of
200, some has to be above, some has to be below. So
what it's basically saying is this is a complicated way of saying
that when they're equal sizes and then this is the worst-case scenario
then half is good. If they're unequal sizes, then המרובה כשר. hamurba
kosher. It's just another way of saying it. That's when you
describe... I'll read it inside, but the
way you describe equal... So let's read that again.
זה הכלל, Ze Haklal, כל מקום שאתה יכול לחלוק את הקינים, kol
makom she'atah yachol lachlok et hakinim, if it's possible to divide it,
שלא יהיו משל אשה אחת בין למעלה בין למטה, shelo yiheyu mishel
isha achat bein l'malah bein l'mata, that one woman's will not necessarily
be both above and below. Meaning you could divide it in a
way, it's a very double negative. You could divide it in a
way where one woman's is all above and the other woman's is
all below, then מחצה כשר kasher? מחצה פסול, Pasul then it's
50%. וכל מקום שאין אתה יכול לחלוק את הקינים עד שיהיו משל
אשה אחת בין למעלה בין למטה, v'kol מקום she'ein atah yachol lachlok
et hakinim ad she'yiheyu mishel isha achat bein l'malah bein l'mata, in
the scenario where one of the women's birds will have to be
both above and below, like in the case of 116 pairs, right,
that one woman that has 200 birds, some of them are going
to have to be below. So in that case, המרובה כשר, hamerubah
kasher, the larger size one is kosher. Of course, the irony about
all of this is that besides which, no,
you don't, because the equal size cases is just a special case
of המרובה כשר. hamerubah kasher. Really all the same rule of המרובה
כשר, hamerubah kasher, right? It's the larger one. If you go by
the larger size, well if they're equal size, then you pick either
one. So, right? So if a case of 116, you say 100
pairs are kosher, then 50 and 50, you say 50 pairs are
kosher, right? So it's really not a different הלכה, halacha, it's really
the same הלכה halacha that you know, if you want to make
it technically the same, you say the one that's not smaller, you
know. So then in an equal size, you pick either one, you
know, but either case anyway, it's really the same rule. I thought
you were saying the irony is
it's almost like חוטא נשכר
choteh niscar because he shouldn't
have been doing any of this anyway.
Well, that's the whole point of this whole פרק, which is like
you said, you're not allowed to ask for instructions for permission. So
once you do it, you're definitely going to do some
stuff wrong, but there's a likelihood that you'll also do
other things right.
So someone actually has a question, they go to the בית המדרש,
Beit HaMidrash, or they happen to go to the סנהדרין Sanhedrin while
they're there anyways, and the rabbis say, you know what, I'd rather
not hear your question, but go ahead. What do they say? What
do they actually tell him?
I don't know, that's not the sense one gets.
But they entertain the question and tell him the answer?
Yeah, yeah, apparently. Okay, but anyway, so this is the rule. Unequal
sizes, if it's all above or all below, then any time everything
is above, everything is below, it's only half. If you split it,
the rule is you go by the larger group, that amount. You
don't know it all came from the larger group. If the larger
group had 100, then you know that 100 pairs were kosher.
Again, not necessarily all from that person. And in the case of
equal sizes, half is just an application of that rule. Now we
go on to the next משנה. mishnah. חטאת לזו ועולה לזו. chatat
lazu v'olah lazu. Okay, that was a case, if you remember, all
of this is a direct parallel of the first פרק. So חטאת
chatat gets mixed up with an עולה. olah. What's the הלכה? halacha?
A definite חטאת chatat and a definite עולה olah. designated? Everybody? They
all have to die, right? Because you can't play around there. There's
no latitude. Right? It's a חטאת chatat and an עולה. olah
So, but you didn't ask. Okay, so you got, so this כהן
kohen once again didn't ask. If he asked, they all would have
had to die. So עשה כולם למעלה, מחצה כשר ומחצה פסול. mechetza
kasher u'mechetza pasul. So again, let's say you have 50 חטאות chatatot
get mixed up with 50 עולות. olahs? They've been differentiated, not undifferentiated.
So you would have had to let them all die, but you
went ahead and, you know, Rifka here had an influence on the
כהן kohen and said how could you let these poor birds die?
So he went ahead and he did them all on the top
half. But at least for a purpose, okay.
Okay, and he did them all, so he did all of them
above, so half are kosher. The ones that were עולות olahs, are
kosher, and the ones that were מחצה פסול, Pasul the ones that
were the חטאת chatat or the עולה. ola עשה כולם למטה, asah
kulam l'mata, he did them all below, מחצה כשר ומחצה פסול. mechetza
kasher u'mechetza pasul. So also half are kosher. The ones that were
a חטאת chatat is good, the one that was an עולה ola.
was not good. So if you had asked, we would have said
let them all die, but you didn't ask, you went ahead and
did it. So half of them are going to be kosher if
you did them all above or all below.
What's the point of saying half are kosher if you don't know
whose are kosher?
Well,
I mean, how you would satisfy the דיני ממונות dinei mamonot aspect
of it
afterwards, you would probably join in the money and make stipulations. Like
if we knew that 20 חטאות chatatot, were kosher but we didn't
know if they were mine or yours,
right, then what we would do is, and we knew that between
us we needed to bring 30, so we'd take 10 more and
we would share in the cost and we'd make a stipulation and
we'd sanctify it, whatever, based on a condition, etc. Exactly. Okay, so
that's, but this פרק, this מסכת masechet is not interested in how
you would solve the, sort of, yeah, fix it, just what's good
right now.
Okay, now חצי למעלה וחצי למטה, chetzi l'malah v'chetzi l'mata, now if
you did half above half below, then nothing is good. Exactly. שתיהם
פסולות. shteihem pesulot. Then if it's a case of just two, then
both are פסול. A case of 50 and 50, all are not
good, because you have to assume worst case scenario. שאני אומר, she'ani
omer, I have to assume worst case scenario, חטאת קרבה למעלה, chatat
krevah l'malah, that the חטאות chatases, were done above and they're all
not. not good above or below. Okay so in this case if
you did it half and half, it's the same as if you
had not asked permission altogether. I mean same as if you had
asked permission and nothing is good, but if you went ahead and
did all above or all below, at least fifty percent of them
will be good. You can never go by
what's likely, you can only go by like what's certain.
Exactly. You have to assume worst case scenario. Okay. And you know
presumably on a principle like ספק דאורייתא safek d'oraita or something like
that. I mean same thing if you
went up 70 out of 100 you'd say. Right, I know, I'm
saying.
That was James' question about they have to bring the additional in
order to receive
in order to become טהור tahor and to finish the process exactly.
Okay. Now.
So until then it was pretty much as I said a commentary
on the first פרק. Now we have a case we didn't have
in the first פרק. Yes please.
When these women bring their חטאת chatat and they're standing there, they
go home, you know they bring, how are they going to know
if the כהן Kohen messed up? He, yeah. Well, they assume that
they're that they're done.
And actually the גמרא gemara or it might be the משנה mishna
says further says that basically all they have to do is put
their money in a box and go home and they can assume
by evening they've taken the money out of the box, that they
had a very efficient system, purchased the birds and you know brought
the קרבן korban and did everything correctly. So you're right, in those
types of scenarios, I mean one wonders even there if they did
mess up whose קרבן korban would they have messed up because not
you know everything is sort of generic and at the end of
the day,
so does that really matter?
Right, in those
in those scenarios they have to all assume that it was done
correctly and you're right it's a little ironic that it's talking about
women and the birds since the standard operating procedure was just putting
the money in, meaning you could have imagined another case like a
less frequent one like a מצורע, metzora, you know, or you know
a זב zav or a זבה. zava. A
מצורע? metzora? Anyway certainly זב zav and a זבה. zava. By where's
the חומש? chumash? Where's the חומש? chumash? Here it is. חטיבת גולני?
Chativat Golani?
Anyways you could have imagined cases like that which were not the
יולדת's yoledet case, where people are might actually have been handling the
birds themselves, but in the case of the you know in the
case of the יולדת, yoledet, you're right, the normal operating standard operating
procedure would be you put the money in the box and go
and assume.
Right, assuming they're buying them right there, right, they're buying them right
there they put
the money in the box. In that case it's just putting the
money in yeah and they're just assuming that it was all done
correctly, yeah.
So then what are the implications then for what?
In a special case where they actually brought the birds themselves. I
mean they had an easy process of just putting the money in,
but in theory somebody could still bring the birds themselves.
Even if they did that the כהן kohen still is just going
to they're going to do it and leave.
You mean if the got you mean if this mix-up occurred
in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash right there on the מזבח.
mizbe'ach. Right,
I mean it's a good point, no way of notifying who it
was? I assume if they did not have a good way of
notifying I don't really know למעשה. l'ma'aseh. I assume if they didn't
have a good way of notifying then they probably would have been
מקריב, makriv you know, been
מקריב the extra birds for the sake you know taken extra birds
and sanctified them for the sake of the person who, right the
כהן kohen would. I assume that at the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash,
right if the donor had no idea and they had no way
of notifying the donor then I assume that and then I assume
they would just sort of make it up so they wouldn't just
be out of their own. I'm guessing, I don't know, but it's
a good question. It's a good question. But either that or they
make the person wait till they're done or you know they have
ways of notifying, you know write your write on a self-addressed stamped
envelope. We'll get back to you in our next edition. All right,
good question.
The one that got away. All right, pass the drinks.
All right, now we go. חטאת ועולה סתומה ומפורשת. chatat v'ola stuma
u'mefureshet. Now here's a case where this is actually relatively easy. You've
got a okay, this you've got an עולה ola. on this side,
a חטאת chatat, on this side already designated. What? I don't know,
yeah it's okay. And then you've got here, this is your undifferentiated
and this is your differentiated, meaning so in this actually you do
already have designated one as a חטאת chatat one as an עולה.
ola. So essentially this is just like this, it's designated. This is
a חטאת, chatas this is an עולה. olah? This is a pair
in the middle that is also חטאת עולה, chatat ola, and this
is your undifferentiated. Now they all get mixed up together. Do you
see three pairs? Okay, so basically what you have is two חטאות
chatos, already defined חטאות, chatos two עולות olahs, and one and two
undifferentiated. Okay, so what did you do?
עשה כולן
למעלה
asa kulan
l'mala so you did them all above. So which how much is
כשר? kasher 50
percent, right? So we see
חטאת ועולה כמה סתומה מפורשת. chatat v'ola kama stuma mefureshet. Four four
things which are three pairs. Okay. Now you did them all above.
מחצה כשר ומחצה פסול. mechtza kasher u'mechtza pasul. So right you did
all pairs above so half of the each pair is כשר, kasher,
the half that is going to be an עולה. olah כולן למטה
kulan l'mata all below מחצה כשר ומחצה פסול. mechtza kasher u'mechtza pasul.
All below, מחצה כשר ומחצה פסול, mechtza kasher u'mechtza pasul, half is
כשר, kasher. half is פסול because you did all pairs, so the
half of each pair that's a חטאת chatas is going to be
כשר. kasher, Now חצי chetzi חציין למעלה וחציין למטה, chatzyan lemalah vechatzyan
lematah, half above, half below, so all the ones that are already
predefined, how much is כשר? kasher. The things that are already designated
חטאת chatas and עולה? olah Zero because you have to assume worst
case scenario, you have to assume you got it exactly wrong, correct?
So the סתומה stuma is the סתומה stuma כשר? kasher, Yes, but
okay, so let's read and then I'll comment. What's the סתומה? stuma?
The סתומה stuma is the undifferentiated. אין כשר אלא סתומה, ein kasher
ella stuma, the only thing that's כשר kasher, is the undifferentiated,
והיא מתחלקת ביניהם. vehi mitchaleket beneihem. This is your point, James, which
assumes why did it say a חטאת chatas here and an עולה
olah here and here it said a חטאת chatas, עולה olah, pair?
In the end it's two חטאות, Chataos. two עולות, Olos because it's
assuming that this חטאת chatas belongs to this woman and this עולה
olah belongs to that woman. Okay, so they're already, meaning they're two
women is what it assumes in this scenario, that each woman has
to bring, you know, one and a half קרבנות, korbanos, okay? So
the way they did it is, so you have to bring an
עולה, olah, you have to bring a חטאת, chatas, meaning they've already
brought half of their other obligation. And then you've also jointly owned
these two pairs, alright? And this one has been subdivided חטאת chatas,
עולה olah and this one has not been subdivided. So as far
as this and this, no good, we have to assume it was
exact wrong. As far as this, no good, we have to assume
it was exact wrong. The only thing that's going to be good
is this, okay? But half חטאת, chatas half עולה, olah and it's
divided between you, meaning you assume that each worked half, you know,
you got half credit, you got credit for half of it, you
got credit for half of it, and the rest you'll have to
figure out how to make up. Now the probability is you don't
know which is which and a חטאת, chatas
so you do make it up, and then what?
You get to make it up by stipulating. You buy all the
rest and you stipulate,
it's for me the חטאת chatas was brought for me, for you.
Now the problem with this is, I'm wondering that you did not
stop me, is who's to say that the סתומה stuma was all
good? Right? We assumed that, okay, here's where, here's where the עולה
olah belongs, here's where the חטאת chatas belongs. If you assume worst
case scenario,
חטאת חטאת chatas chatas was up here, עולה עולה olah olah was
down there, and סתומה סתומה stuma stuma was here, right? And that's
כשר, kasher. so that we say that that piece there was כשר.
kasher, But somebody should have said, hey, you're not allowed to do
that, maybe the סתומה stuma was all above and you don't get
credit for the whole סתומה, stuma, only half of it, right? You
understand? Ah, but there's an answer. As soon as I move the
סתומה stuma above, what do I have to do?
I only got to put three above, so I have to move
one of these down here. That makes it good, the חטאת chatas
is good. Do you understand? As soon as I try to make
this a worst case scenario, it counterbalanced by moving something into the
right position. Okay, and the same is true in the opposite. If
I try to move the סתומה stuma down here, I have to
move the עולה olah, up to take its place. So at the
end of the day, one חטאת chatas and one עולה olah is
good, although you don't know which חטאת chatas, and which עולה, olah
right? Which is part of what the ראב"ד Raavad says. The ראב"ד
Raavad reads it that way. It says not literally the סתומה stuma
is כשר, Kosher, but the size of the סתומה stuma is כשר.
Kosher. Okay, because and in that case you have to divide, they
have to sort of they don't know, right?
Who, maybe half the סתומה stuma would be good.
No, but the whole סתומה's stuma good, the amount of the סתומה's.
stuma Worst case scenario, at least half the סתומה. stuma.
No, worst case scenario is both one חטאת chatas and one עולה's
olah, good.
Right, one חטאת, chatas, but I'm saying in those two סתומות. stumas.
Yes, of the actual סתומה stuma itself. Right, but that's why the
ראב"ד Raavad says, it says not mean the סתומה stuma itself is
כשר, Kosher? it means the size, the number of birds equal to
the size of the סתומה. stuma. And that's why it says that
you guys now, or you women now have to divide it up
because you don't know. Maybe it wasn't the סתומה stuma itself which
was כשר, Kosher, maybe another thing was כשר. Kosher. So it's not
clear in the end whose קרבן korban was כשר, Kosher whose קרבן
korban was not. So you have to, you know, bring a new
קרבן korban and stipulate, but at the end you do know that
somehow between the two of you, one חטאת chatas and one עולה
olah. was good. Okay, good. See that? Not as hard as yesterday,
is it? Moving on.
Now חטאות שנתערבו בחובה, chatos shenisarvu bechovah, אין כשר אלא מנין חטאות
שבחובה. ein kasher ella minyan chatos shebechovah. We're again quoting from the
first
פרק. If you have a חטאת, chatas a predefined חטאת chatas. that
gets mixed up in a חובה. chovah. Like you have a חובה
chovah of a hundred pairs and one חטאת chatas, gets mixed up.
So how much can I bring now? This was the very first
משנה mishna we taught. How much can I bring? Can I bring
any עולות? Olos, No,
because as soon as I bring one עולה, Olah, I might be
bringing the pre- the already predefined חטאת. chatas So I cannot bring
any עולות, Olos and I can bring חטאות, Chataos but I can't
bring a hundred, because as soon as I try to bring a
hundred and one, I might be bringing not the extra one חטאת,
Chatas. but I might be bringing from one of these, the counterparts,
and something that is an עולה. olah. So that is the rule
that we learned in the first פרק. One חטאת Chatas. gets mixed
up in an undifferentiated group, in a חובה. chovah. You can only
bring, you can't bring עולות, Olos you can only bring חטאות Chataos
and only based on the size of the original group. Okay, now
we're going to talk about what's missing here is the transition to
the... now we're talking moving from that's the לכתחילה, Lechatchila, now we're
talking to about the בדיעבד Bedieved case. The כהן kohen. went and
did it. שנים בחטאת, Shnayim Bechatas,
let's say you have the size of your חובה Chova is twice
the size of your חטאת. Chatas Okay, so you have a חובה
Chova of I don't know, a hundred pairs. All right, we'll make
it easier. You have a חובה Chova of four birds. Okay, two
pairs. Okay, this is your, we'll call it סתומה. Stuma. That's your
חובה Chova and you have two חטאות.
Chataos What's the difference between חובה Chova and סתומה? Stuma? What? What's
the difference between חובה Chova and... Nothing, nothing.
סתומה Stuma is just clearer that it means undifferentiated. But חובה Chova
also means undifferentiated. Okay, so you have two חטאות Chataos. that get
mixed up into your סתומה Stuma which is your חובה. Chova. Okay?
Okay, so this is twice the size of the חטאות Chataos that
got mixed up. Now, if we were asking permission, how many would
we say that, what would we say for this case?
Wait, wait, what's your scenario?
You have two birds.
Two birds from חובה Chova went into your...
These are birds, not pairs, okay, two birds that are
חטאת. Chatas I also, instead of ח, Ches, I can just do
ח Ches for חטאת Chatas. and ס Samech for סתומה. Stuma. I
don't have to worry where those two ח. Ches. Okay, two חטאות
Chataos. birds that fly into your four undifferentiated birds. How many, if
I were asking permission, could I bring? Two. Two, two חטאות. Chataos.
Right, I can't bring any עולות Olos that I might be getting
from this, I can only bring two חטאות Chataos anymore, and I
might be getting from within this group, and therefore I'm limited to
two. So if I was asking permission, it would be two חטאות.
Chataos Let's see what happens if I didn't ask permission. שנים בחטאת
Shnayim Bechatas מחצה כשר Kosher מחצה פסול. Half is כשר, Kosher. half
is פסול. Now in which scenario? It's assuming in a scenario that,
let me just double check, that I said half was above and
half was below. Hold on a minute.
Yeah, half above and half below.
So I didn't ask permission. If I asked permission,
permission you would tell me two חטאות. Chataos I didn't ask permission,
I did half above, half below. So I did three and three.
So let's talk about best case scenario and worst case scenario. Okay,
so best case scenario, the חטאות Chataos are going to be where
they belong,
right? Everybody with me here? Yeah, the חטאות Chataos are going to
be where they belong, and one סתומה Stuma here and three סתומה
Stuma up here. So what's going to be the, what will that
be?
Everything's good. One...
No, it's the best case scenario. No, if even though it's best,
not everything is good because I cannot have the סתומה Stuma as
עולות, olos I can only get two עולות olos out of the
סתומה. Stuma. So even in the best case
scenario, I have five of the birds being כשר. Kosher, That's, that's
best, right? You with me? Right, so as best case is five.
Worst case is the flip, right? The חטאות chataos are exactly where
they don't belong, yes? Okay,
so in that case what is כשר? kasher, Three.
What?
Three. No, three birds. Okay, let's, whoops, so let's see if that
works. So what does it say?
It's on half to half though.
Well, it's half
of the total.
Six is the total, so it's half of the total. But how
do you get three over there again?
Because three, one סתומה Stuma is good, one
pair of a סתומה Stuma and half a סתומה. Stuma.
This סתומה's Stuma כשר, kasher these two סתומה Stuma are כשר.
kasher Okay, so, so it's half is כשר kasher but with the,
but more of the opposite than the things that flew in because
the things that flew in you have to assume are in the
exact wrong position. Okay, so in that case מחצה כשר kasher מחצה
פסול, half is good, half is not good, but again, not just
you, not an equal amount of חטאת Chatas and עולה, olah, actually
two-thirds of the עולות olos are good and one, you know, half
is good and of that half, two-thirds of that half are, are
עולות olos and one-third is a חטאת. Chatas All right, but that
half is good. Now, חטאת ושנים שבחובה, Chatas ushnayim shebechova, let's say
it's the reverse. The חטאת Chatas birds that flew in were twice
as big as the חובה Chova birds. So
let's flip the numbers.
Okay, the number of the predefined חטאות chataos that flew in were
twice as big as the סתומה. Stuma. Okay, so best case scenario,
okay, best case scenario is חטאת חטאת חטאת, Chatas Chatas Chatas, right?
And then here חטאת סתומה סתומה, Chatas Stuma Stuma, yes? Because this
is where the חטאת chatas, belongs, is on the bottom, and therefore
four חטאות chataos. and two סתומה. Stuma. So best case scenario all
these are כשר kasher and these two are כשר. kasher. Again, we
have five, yes? Everybody with me? No, I mean these are all
כשר, Kasher חטאת chatas, is where it belongs. Oh, no, I'm sorry,
four. Yes, four, four. Excuse me, four. This one has to be,
this one has to be... Okay, good, four. Now, that's best-case scenario.
Worst-case scenario is the opposite. חטאת, chatas, חטאת, chatas, חטאת, chatas חטאת,
chatas אשם, asham,
אשם. asham.
You only have one.
How much is kosher? One? Two? No, one, one of them.
Right, only one.
Because the חטאת chatas. has to be from the חובה.
chovah. Why isn't the חטאת chatat, on the bottom good?
Oh, I'm sorry.
It should be... you're right, you're right.
Two, two, two. Okay, good. Yes, yes, you're right. Two. Got it?
None of the חטאות chataos. on the bottom is good and one
of these סתומות stumos is good. So that's two. Okay, so how
does... so that is the size of the original חובה. chovah. Alright.
So,
let's take a look.
חטאת שתיים בחובה, Chatas shtayim bechovah, if there's twice as many חטאות
chataos that flew into the חובה chovah and you brought them half
above, half
below, המניין שבחובה כשר, haminyan shebechovah kasher, the size of the original
group, of the original סתומה, stumah, that is what is going to
be כשר, and you'll have to assume that they're כשר as חטאות.
chataos. Although actually you can't say that definitely because it's possible that
there was another scenario and that one was... oh, no, no, it's
definitely true that there were two כשר חטאות. chataos.
In the worst-case, best-case scenario you had two כשר חטאות chataos and
in this case you had two כשר חטאות.
chataos Right, so in that case you would assume that they were
two כשר חטאות. chataos Okay, so there you go. If it's twice...
if the birds that flew... if the סתומה stumah group is bigger,
it's half, with the bias being against the, you know, towards the
עולה. olah And if they... and if the bird that flew in
is bigger, in this case twice as big, then it goes by
the size of the original
one. אין כשר אלא מניין עולה... Ein kasher ela minyan olah... did
I skip it? No, וכן, vechein, and now it just has the
opposite in reverse which is easy. עולה שנתערבה בחובה, Olah shenisarev bechovah,
if you have the birds that flew in were an עולה, olah
אין כשר אלא מניין עולה שבחובה. ein kasher ela minyan olah shebechovah.
So then if you were asking permission you would say just do
the number of עולות olot, that were in the original group. Do
half of the original group, right? That's if you were asking permission.
Yes, that's the very first thing we learned. One עולה olah. flies
into a group, you do how much if you're asking permission? You
do all the עולות olot. of the original group, half the size
of the original group. But you didn't ask permission. So what did
you do? So חובה שתיים בעולה, chovah shtayim be'olah,
so if they were... the original group was twice the size of
the עולה olah and you did them half above, half below, מחצה
כשר ומחצה פסול, mechetza kasher u'mechetza pasul, half kosher, half pasul,
just like we said by the חטאת. chatat עולה שתיים בחובה, Olah
shtayim bechovah, if the עולות olot, that flew in were twice as
big as the חובה, chovah, then we say
המניין שבחובה כשר, haminyan shebechovah kasher, the size of that are in
the חובה chovah are כשר. Now by the way, you realize that...
no, forget it. Okay.
So why would you do half above and half below if you'd
get a much better outcome by doing all on the bottom? If
you know four חטאות flew into two birds, you can get five
good חטאות on the bottom.
Because this כהן kohen who wasn't asking permission, he also didn't figure
out anything out. He just... he thought... maybe
he just thought the easiest scenario is, he thought it was a
normal undifferentiated group and he did what you would do with an
undifferentiated group, half above and half below and יהיה מה שיהיה.
yehei mah sheyehei.
But if you... if you know what you're doing and you're really
trying to maximize it, then yes, then if חטאות get mixed up,
then you should do them all, you know, below, and if עולות
olot get mixed up you should do them all above. Right? But
again, you're not supposed to. You're supposed to just do the... the
half of the size of, you know, מניין חטאות שבחובה minyan chataos
shebechovah or מניין עולות שבחובה. minyan olos shebechovah.
How many were actually sacrificed at a given time? Was it a
hundred of them or just... I thought each individual who had to
sacrifice would have maybe go give to a specific כהן kohen and
there wouldn't be... it seems very... Right. So that's... you're right.
Having large size groups are unlikely. You can imagine a case of
a יולדת yoledes because a יולדת yoledes would have to bring a
קרבן korban even for a miscarriage. So you could imagine a case
about maybe a woman had a couple of miscarriages and, you know,
and then if you're not living in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, you bundle them
up and you wait till you're coming to the בית המקדש. Beis
Hamikdash. But you know, a lot of this is more theoretical obviously
than practical. They like to be... thinking... so fine... yeah. I mean,
if they put all
the money in the box, they could have a hundred pair.
Yeah, so that raises an interesting question which this מסכת maseches never
identifies, which is what defines, right, if the... every פרק said if
I
have one group of four and one group of four, even if
I'm the same owner and they get mixed up, they're two groups
of four, they're not one big group of eight. So what defines
the parameter of when is something defined as separate groups? Because even
the same owner can have separate groups, it's not just different owners.
And what defines when it's considered one big group? Is it that
I sanctified them and purchased them all at the same time? What
defines when it's considered one big group? Is it that I sanctify
them and purchase them all at the same time? You know, what
exactly defines those? That's not spelled out in our מסכת. Masechet. Okay,
let's go to משנה ו. Mishna Vav. האישה שאמרה הרי עלי קן
כשאלד זכר. Ha'ishah she'amrah harei alai kan kesheyelled zachar. A woman that
said I accept upon myself in addition to whatever קרבן korban, I
have to bring, to give a nest of birds when if I
have a male child. So this obviously reflects a bias towards desire
of having male children. Even nowadays I believe they say
that people they've taken these surveys,
people prefer to have boys. In families only allowed one child right,
well that I know for sure, but anyway, but I think it's
just a reflection of how society is biased in favor of men.
So anyway, so a woman says that, הרי עלי קן כשאלד זכר.
harei alai kan kesheyelled zachar. Now remember if somebody donates a bird
קרבן, korban then we assume two עולות, olot both of them, and
obviously can't donate a חטאת, chatat. so they're both עולות. olot Then
what happens? ילדה זכר, yaldah zachar, she had her boy. מביאה שתי
קינים, meviah shtei kinim, she brings two pairs of birds. אחת לנדרה,
achat lenidrah, one for her vow, which are both עולות, olot ואחת
לחובתה, ve'achat lechovatah, and one for her obligation which is a חטאת
chatat and an עולה. olah, נתנתם לכהן, netanatam lakohen, she gave it
to the כהן. Kohen הכהן צריך לעשות ג' פרידין מלמעלה ואחת מלמטה.
hakohen tzarich la'asot gimel pereidin milmalah ve'achat milmatah. He has to do
three above, one below. Okay, and it sounds as though that also
here's the question: did she give him a group of four of
which you take out three and one or two groups of two?
And then he can't do any three above, he has to make
sure he does, you know, he does two from one of the
groups and one from the other. So that's not spelled out. But
anyway, that's what would be if he was doing the right thing,
he would have
done three above and one below.
פרידה preidah is individual bird. פרידה preidah is an individual bird, yes.
We not had that word yet? That's correct, an individual bird. לא
עשה כן, lo asah ken, he did not do what he was
supposed to. אלא ב' מלמעלה וב' מלמטה. ela bet milmalah uvet milmatah.
And he thought like any other types of birds, half above, half
below, wasn't paying attention. ולא נמלך, velo nimlach, and he didn't ask
anybody ahead of time. Now what's her obligation? So here רבקה, Rivka,
this assumes that he was able to get back to her and
tell her that there was a mistake. Okay, so it makes it
now she has to bring the rest, which is not very fair
clearly because it was his fault and there is a גמרא Gemara
in גיטין Gittin that talks about whether there's some liability for כהנים
kohanim that through their error cause loss to the owner, but that
is not being addressed here. I mean, that gets into basically it's
a type of malpractice. So there's legal malpractice and medical malpractice and
there's קרבנות korbanos malpractice.
So anyway, but that's a discussion in גיטין. Gittin. So here, now
her קרבן Korban might not have been fully satisfied, well certainly wasn't
because he did two above, two below. What does she have to
do in order to make sure it's fully satisfied? צריכה להביא עוד
פרידה אחת. tzrichah lehavi od preidah achat. She has to bring one
more bird because one bird was done wrong, right? It should have
been three above and one below, and it was two and two.
So one that was done below was an עולה olah done as
a חטאת. chatat So she has to make up an עולה, Olah
right? Because she has to make up one of the ones that
belonged above. Is this something we don't know? Because we're going to
get to more complicated cases. ויקריבנה מלמעלה, veyakrivennah milmalah, and she'll bring
it above. That is all if it's ממין אחד. mimin echad. That's
if it's all the same type of bird, all תור tor or
בני יונה. benei yonah. Now I had said in the second פרק,
I spoke, I misspoke, because there they introduce this idea and I
said, well, this isn't really about permutations, but here
it actually is about permutations, this idea that every pair has to
be all of one type. Oh, both תור tor or both בני
יונה. benei yonah. And now we're going to use that to make
this more complicated. Okay, so
let's take a look. משני מינים, mishnei minim,
let's say she brought one of her pair was תור tor and
one was בני יונה, benei yonah, and they were different מינים, minim,
and the כהן went ahead and he did three above, one below
two and two. The pair of עולה olah have to be the
same
type? Yeah, that's a good point, it's assumed that, that's correct, it's
assuming that. You're right, I mean that wasn't said explicitly before. There's
no way around it. Yeah, but we do say that they're given
as she said a קן, kan, so ממין אחד. mimin echad. Let
me think as I continue to describe the case, let me think
if that's a necessary condition here. Okay, let's spell this out. So
she says two. Now the כהן went ahead and he did two
above and two below. He forgot which ones he did above, which
ones he did below. Okay, it's also we also have to assume,
although this isn't spelled out in the משנה, Mishna, that she forgot
like which ones she brought as her חטאת chatat? and which ones
she brought as her נדר. neder. Okay, so what are the implications
of this? So in that case, משני מינים תביא שתיים, mishnei minim
tavi shtayim, she has to bring two. Why? Because I think we
are still assuming that he brought we're still assuming that of each
pair I guess so. He brought one of above and one below.
That wasn't a total mistake because then he could have brought one
whole pair below and one whole pair above, that we're not assuming.
So we're assuming his נדר נדר Neder Neder and חובה Chovah and
this would be whatever this well one would be עולה עולה חטאת
Olah Olah Chatat because that was correct. Okay. The only problem was
that the נדר Neder had to go above. Okay, so wait why
are we assuming he got everything exactly wrong? No this is right.
No I'm saying why aren't we assuming? Because basically he took that
separate pair that is an implicit assumption in this case the discussions
of ראשונים Rishonim because not everything is spelled out in this case.
Okay but it is assuming that this we're assuming was right so
not assuming that he did a whole pair below. Okay so you're
assuming those weren't designated? Yeah these were from non-designated. Right but it
could be worse cause that's what I was asking why are we
assuming? Because we're assuming each pair is from a different מין. Min.
Okay so in this case the problem was that this was done
incorrectly okay so this has to be made up. Now if these
were all one מין Min all תור Tor so you know you
make up one תור. Tor. But if if some of these two
were תור Tor and these were בני יונה Bnei Yonah or the
reverse then this has to be made up and you see here
it is by this it has to be paired. This has to
be made up of the same type as the one that as
its as its pair. But since you don't know you gotta bring
both so therefore you have to bring two. You have to bring
one תור Tor one בני יונה Bnei Yonah and do them both
above in order to make in order to meet with that one
above okay and you don't know which it has to be. So
basically he's gotta bring from the same מין Min that he did.
He can't say like since תורים Torim and בני יונה Bnei Yonah
are okay I could just bring it as a בני יונה Bnei
Yonah cause I could have brought a בני יונה Bnei Yonah to
begin with anyway. No well that's a variation of James's point which
is that you would have thought that at least by a נדר
Neder that you know that the idea of being a pair of
a tight unit pair is not there. No but even on the
makeup you have to do the same way. I know well once
you've brought one of the pair you have to bring the other.
Okay i guess what you could do is you could ignore the
one that was brought above and bring a new pair that you
could also do. You could bring two of the same and bring
a new pair but if you want to keep that as part
of your נדר Neder then you have to bring two now if
you don't... One of each kind? One of each kind. We don't
assume he's got to bring two of the same kind. I got
it. But what you're saying is you could ignore that and bring
a new נדר. Neder. Bring a new two to satisfy your נדר
Neder but if you want to keep that as good you have
to bring one of each kind. Okay so that's that. משני מינים
תביא שתים. Mishnei minim tavi shtayim. Two birds. Right. Either way two
birds. Exactly. משני מינים תביא שתים. Mishnei minim tavi shtayim. Bring two.
Now פירשה נדרה. Pirshah nidrah. Now let's say she said explicitly I'm
going to bring two birds of תור Tor or two birds of
בני יונה. Bnei Yonah. She said explicitly but of course then she
forgot what she said she forgot what she brought the כהן forgot
what he did. Okay everybody forgot everything. Okay so in that case
okay צריכה והביא עוד ג' פרידים ממין אחד. Tzricha vahavi od gimel
peridim mimi echad. If they are all of now if they are
if they are ממין אחד. Mimi echad. Hold on. Oh okay so
basically she brought everything of the same type but again she forgot
what she brought. She either brought all four as pigeons or all
four as turtledoves. Okay she forgot which one she brought she forgot
what she had originally said. Okay so it's sort of like everything
is back you know so you have to do everything correctly. So
this is of course good because this she didn't she didn't make
a נדר Neder about that those two are definitely good. Okay these
two basically it's very simple these two this is obviously פסול but
you know what that also is פסול because we don't know not
פסול it's a כשר קרבן korban but we don't know that it
satisfies the נדר Neder because it could have been it could have
been the wrong one. Right. Meaning she what do you mean it
could have been the wrong one? She could have said תור Tor
and she could have made a mistake and brought a בני יונה
Bnei Yonah to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash she just doesn't know
she brought the right. Yeah she she doesn't remember what she said
she doesn't remember what she brought and so on. So what does
she have to now bring? She has to now bring two pairs
right? Because this is תור Tor and this is בני יונה. Bnei
Yonah. She doesn't she basically she doesn't know she satisfied her all
her obligation. And one's a vow and one's a... No these are
both for her vow. The עולה olah. and the חובה. Chovah. Oh
so one fulfills her vow and one is extra and basically playing
it safe. She's obligated a pair of תור Tor or a pair
of בני יונה Bnei Yonah she doesn't know which she could she
has no idea whether she actually satisfied her obligation based on what
was brought. You can't cut you know cut one out because you
don't even remember what those were so that you could eliminate. So
to play it safe she has to bring four. So it says
להביא עוד ג' פרידים. Lehavi od gimel peridim. Oh so why ג'?
Gimel? ג' פרידים ממין אחד. Gimel peridim mimi echad. So maybe it
is... Hold on oh right I'm sorry I was jumping ahead. You
were trying to make it less difficult. So I'm sorry I'm sorry
I was jumping. And I was jumping ahead to the last case.
In this case, in this case she knows, excuse me, these were
all, that at least דעתו da'ato was נוח. noach. And she knows
that these were all what they תור, tor, okay? So in that
case, this is what she would have to bring if she definitely
did not satisfy her obligation. But here she knows she did bring
one תור. tor. She knows she brought a תור? tor? What? She
doesn't know whether she vowed יונה. yonah. She doesn't know what she
vowed, but it is known that these were all תור. tor. Should
she bring one more תור? tor? Well, so then she brings one
fewer תור. tor. That's three. Okay, so that gets us all of
one type. But if they're different types, and then she doesn't even
know what was brought here, right? In that case, she doesn't even
know, then she has to bring four. Yes? Clear? It still could
be different types. It just says, it could be she just totally
forgets what was brought. Right. Okay, but different types is a different,
different scenario though. Okay, if she knows what this was and the
classic scenario would be all the same type, then she can eliminate
it from one of the things she brought and it's three. If
she doesn't know what this was and a classic scenario would be
different types and nobody knows exactly what was done, then she has
to bring four. Since we're not, we're never assuming here that you
know, that she probably did what she said she was going to
do because people take these things seriously. You know what I mean?
Like if I vowed to bring a תור, tor, I assume I
brought my תור. tor. I understand, I understand. Okay, all of this...
yeah. How much of this is realistic? I assume very little. Okay,
moving on. Where were we? קבע נדרה. Kava nidrah. Now קבע נדרה
kava nidrah means the following. She says, I am vowing to bring
this קן kan together with my... my קרבן korban for יולדת, yoledet,
which basically means that now it has to be brought as a
group. And the way that's defined as a group means that all
three עולות olos. have to be brought together. A חטאת chatas is
never brought, never done at the same place, but the נדר neder
is two עולות and this קרבן korban for יולדת yoledet is one
עולה olah. and so... and one of them, one of the two
is an עולה. olah. So when she says, Together... I'm going to
bring it together with my קרבן korban. for יולדת, yoledet, it means
all three עולות have to be brought together. Okay, let's see what
this translates into. קבע נדרה צריכה להביא עוד חמש פרידין ממין אחד,
משני מינים תביא שש. Kava nidrah, tzrichah lehavi od chamesh peridin mimin
echad, mishnei minim tavi sheish. She has to bring five and from
two she has to bring six. Now, what does that mean? So,
let me just make sure I got this right. So she goes
ahead and it's the same thing. So ממין אחד, mimin echad, the
only thing that's different is that she has to bring not only
her נדר neder again if she doesn't know what was done correctly,
but because it's together with the קרבן חטאת, korban chatat, she has
to bring another bird for the... for... I mean together with the
קרבן עולה, korban olah, excuse me, she has to bring another bird
together with the עולה. olah. Okay, so you have to add the
עולה. olah, So... I mean, why? Why? Because it all has to
be together. Because it all has to be together, that was קבע
נדרה. kava nidrah. Why doesn't it have to be together with the
חטאת? chatas Because we're assuming that it's together. I don't know, because
these are עולות together with the עולה. olah. That's the assumption. So
in that case, again, if there's a big mix-up, she doesn't know...
are we dealing with ממין אחד mimin echad or... ממין אחד, mimin
echad, let's start with. Okay, so in that case, now let's deal
with it. Let's assume that it was totally not good, right? Totally
not good, everything was not good and she has to do it
now as a makeup. What would she do as a makeup? So
now what she would do is she would have to bring... she
would have to go ahead and bring six, right? Now not really,
because even though it's brought together with the עולה, olah it doesn't
have to be the same מין min as the עולה. olah. So
she could really bring five if she's doing everything as a makeup.
It can be brought all at the same time, she doesn't remember
exactly which one she vowed. Fine, but either way it's all being
brought at the same time together with an עולה olah and she
is... it's five. Okay, that would be in that case. Why? I'm
not following the scenario here. She said, I'm going to bring my
נדר neder together with my קרבן. Right. And she doesn't remember... she
doesn't remember... No... she doesn't remember what... whether she vowed תור tor
or בני יונה. bnei yonah. Right. We'll assume a case that was
pure שוא, shav, right? So she said, I'm going to bring definitely
one, she doesn't remember which one, okay? And therefore she's got to
bring this to make up for her נדר neder because here we're
going to assume nothing was good. I'll get to the fact that
one of them must have been good in a minute. And she
does this to make up for her נדר neder and one thing
for her עולה. olah, Okay. So that's basically what she's going to
have to bring now. That's in that case. That's in a standard
case. Now why, hold on, why if it is all ממין אחד,
mimin echad, can she not go ahead and eliminate... Oh, because this
was not good. The reason she can't eliminate... is because even though
this she knows was a טעות, to'os, it's not good because she
has to bring everything correctly together. You've got to bring them all
together. She has no right, she can't eliminate this, so makes everything
not good. This was not good and that was not good because
they weren't three, they have to be three to be good. And
therefore she's bringing this and this way she knows she's safe. Okay?
Because she's bringing תור tor and בני יונה b'nei yonah together with
the other. So that's the case of five. Now, when you say
she's bringing all three together, then we can't say בדיעבד b'dieved if
one of them was brought separately, so? Apparently not. Okay. Now, משני
מינים תביא שש. mishnei minim tavi shesh. If there's two מינים, minim,
she brings six. Now how the heck would she ever have to
bring six? This is everything. Because she doesn't—two מינים minim means that
over here, the original set had both types and you don't know
which was which, right? Now you remember another הלכה halacha we taught
last פרק, which is actually, this is I think the same הלכה,
halacha, which is that the עולה and חטאת chatas. have to be
of the same type. So since she has to bring another עולה,
and if she knew everything was a תור, tor, then that would—this
would be a תור. tor. But if she doesn't know what the
חטאת was, then she has to bring two עולות. She has to
bring six because she has to bring that, because depending on what
was brought as a חטאת. Yes? Pretty clear? More or less? Okay.
So, okay. Okay, I think we will end here, which is too
bad because I thought we were going to get to all the
cases. We have one last little scenario based on that which we
will do tomorrow. But besides that, we are mostly done. So give
yourself